Peter：让我们再看看将滚动/俯仰/偏转角度转换为旋转矩阵。
Peter: Lets have another look at converting roll/pitch/yaw angles to a rotation matrix.
我们使用刚才介绍的功能;rpy2r，我要传球了
We use the function that we introduced a moment ago; rpy2r, and I’m going to pass in a roll
角度为0.3弧度，俯仰弧度为pi/2弧度，偏航角为0.5弧度。和
angle of 0.3 radians, a pitch radians of pi/2 radians, and a yaw angle of 0.5 radians. And
和以前一样，我们有一个正交旋转矩阵。
as before we have an orthonormal rotation matrix.
现在我要将其转换回滚动/俯仰/偏转角度。为此，我使用反函数
Now I’m going to convert that back to roll/pitch/yaw angles. To do that I use the inverse function
tr2rpy和我传递我们刚刚计算的旋转矩阵，这里是滚动/俯仰/偏航
tr2rpy and I pass in the rotation matrix that we just computed, and here are the roll/pitch/yaw
角。你会发现它们与我们传入的那些完全不同。中间角度，
angles. You’ll notice they are quite different to those that we passed in. The middle angle,
俯仰角是相同的，它的pi/2。滚动角度从0.3变为0，并且
the pitch angle is the same, its pi/2. The roll angle has changed from 0.3 to 0, and
偏航角从0.5变为0.8。
the yaw angle has changed form 0.5 to 0.8.
如果你很敏锐，你会注意到0.8是0.3和0.5的总和。所以我们的一个
If you are sharp you’ll have noticed that 0.8 is the sum of 0.3 and 0.5. So one of our
角度已经为0，并且偏航角已经达到原始侧倾角和偏航角之和。
angles has got 0, and the yaw angle has gone to the sum of the original roll and yaw angles.
这里发生了什么？
What’s going on here?
这是一种称为奇点的条件，它以任何三角度序列出现
This is a condition known as singularity, and it occurs in any three-angle sequence
表示方向。它发生在滚动/俯仰/偏转角度，它发生在欧拉
representation of an orientation. It occurs for roll/pitch/yaw angles, it occurs for Euler
角。它始终发生在中间角度取特定值时，以及滚动/俯仰时
angles. It always occurs when the middle angle takes on a particular value, and for roll/pitch
/偏角，俯仰角等于pi/2，导致奇点状态。
/yaw angles the pitch angle is equal to pi/2, leads to the singularity condition.
这种情况也被称为万向节锁的相当不寻常的名称。如果你曾经
This condition is also known by the rather unusual name of gimbal lock. If you’ve ever
看过电影“阿波罗13号”你会听说过这个词。
seen the movie Apollo 13 you will have heard that term used.
阿波罗13号实际上是我最喜欢的电影之一。这是一个戏剧化的
Apollo 13 is actually one of my favourite movies. It’s a dramatisation of the very
1970年着名的阿波罗13号登月仪式。
famous Apollo 13 mission to the moon back in 1970.
宇航员：Ok休斯顿我们在这里遇到了问题。
Astronaut: Ok Houston we’ve had a problem here.
地面管制员：这是休斯顿，请再说一遍。
Ground Controller: This is Houston, say again please.
宇航员：好吧休斯顿我们遇到了问题。我们有一个主B总线不足。
Astronaut: Alright Houston we’ve had a problem. We’ve had a Main B Bus undervolt.
彼得：航天器内置了一个有缺陷的部件并最终造成了
Peter: There was a faulty component built into the spacecraft and eventually caused
大爆炸。登月失败了，宇航员真的很幸运
a massive explosion. The moon landing was aborted and the astronauts were really lucky
活着回到地球。
to get back to earth alive.
爆炸给宇航员和美国宇航局地勤人员带来了各种各样的问题;
The explosion presented the astronauts and NASA ground staff with all kinds of problems;
节省船员的氧气，去除多余的二氧化碳，处理电力短缺，
saving the crew’s oxygen, removing excess carbon dioxide, dealing with power shortage,
并制定了让宇航员安全返回地球的战略。
and devising a strategy for getting the astronauts safely back to Earth.
这场戏剧性危机的一个相当模糊的因素是万向节锁定。这是一个非常深奥的
A rather more obscure element of this dramatic crisis is gimbal lock. It is a pretty esoteric
术语。这是一个非常令人讨厌的术语，我很确定它也是第一个，也许是最后一个
term. It’s a very geeky term, and I'm pretty sure it's also the first and perhaps the last
它将在好莱坞电影中被提及！
time it will ever be mentioned in a Hollywood movie!
问题首先是由地面管制员接收，因为他们监控
The problem first of all was picked up by the ground controllers, as they monitor the
船上的船员试图稳定受灾的航天器。
crew onboard trying to stabilise the stricken spacecraft.
地面管制员：13，休斯顿。我们看到你在那里接近万向节锁。星期三
Ground Controller: 13, Houston. We see you getting close to gimbal lock there. We’d
比如你把MainA上的所有QuadC调出来。主A上的QuadC1，C2，C3和C4，以及
like you to bring up all Quad C’s on Main A. Quad C1, C2, C3 and C4 on Main A, and also
将B3和B4带到MainA上。
bring B3 and B4 up on Main A.
彼得：飞行员拼命想让它远离万向节锁定状态。
Peter: The pilot was trying desperately to keep it away from the Gimbal lock condition.
地面管制员：13，休斯顿。你读过吗？
Ground Controller: 13, Houston. Do you read?
宇航员：是的我们得到了它。
Astronaut: Yeah we got it.
彼得：阿波罗号太空船的飞行控制装置就像在美国国家航空航天局的测试台上看到的那样。
Peter: The Apollo spacecraft’s flying controls were something like those seen in this NASA testbed.
这种万向节锁定条件与我们在MATLAB中查看的示例有关
This gimbal lock condition is related to the example that we were looking at in MATLAB
刚才，但在这种情况下，在美国国家航空航天局的案件中，他们正在处理真实的物理问题
a moment ago but in this case, in the NASA case, they were dealing with real physical
万向节。那么让我们来看看物理万向节及其工作原理。
gimbals. So let's have a look at physical gimbals and how they work.
万向节是一种简单的机制，用于保持像指南针这样精致的乐器
A Gimbal is a simple mechanism that's used to keep a delicate instrument like a compass
或者一个时钟，当它安装在车辆或正在经历相当大的船只上时的水平
or a clock, level when it's mounted on a vehicle or a vessel that's undergoing considerable
运动。这里的第一个例子是指南针，我们称之为双轴万向节，所以罗盘
motion. And the first example here is a compass in we call a two axis Gimbal, so the compass
可围绕此特定轴旋转，然后整个组件围绕此旋转
can rotate around this particular axis and then that whole assembly rotates around this
轴。或者如果指南针的底座安装在船上并且船正在滚动和俯仰
axis. Or if the base of the compass was mounted on the ship and the ship is rolling and pitching
指南针将保持水平。这个时钟表示同样的，它的
then the compass is going to remain level. The same for this clock indicated here, its
首先可以围绕此轴自由旋转，然后可以围绕此轴自由旋转。
first free to rotate around this axis and then it's free to rotate around this axis.
如果我将这个盒子放在我乘坐帆船的舱内的桌子上，那么时钟就是
If I place this box on the table in my cabin on board a sailing ship then the clock is
即使船舶经受相当大的运动，它仍将保持水平。这个
going to remain level even though the ship is undergoing quite considerable motion. This
最后一个例子有点复杂，它包含了我们所说的三轴万向节。
last example is a little bit more complex it contains what we call a three axis Gimbal.
在第一种情况下，指南针可以围绕该轴自由旋转，然后是整个旋转
In the first case then, the compass is free to rotate around this axis and then that whole
装配可绕该轴自由旋转，最后所有内部装配都是
assembly is free to rotate around this axis and finally all that inner assembly is
可以绕此轴自由旋转。
free to rotate around this axis.
万向节广泛用于工程系统，这是万向节的示意图
Gimbals are widely used in engineering systems and this is a schematic of a gimbal that was
前面提到的Apollo月球模块导航系统的一部分
part of the navigation system for the Apollo lunar module that was referred to earlier
在电影里。关键部分是所谓的稳定平台，它包含在内
in the movie. The key component is what's called the stabilized platform and it consists
三个陀螺仪快速旋转，他们保持这个特定的组件显示在这里
of three gyroscopes spinning quickly and they keep this particular assembly shown here in
蓝色相对于宇宙的固定方向。现在因为车辆在哪
blue at a fixed orientation with respect to the universe. Now because the vehicle in which
它的安装将是旋转和平移，然后我们需要一些机械连接的方式
it's mounted is going to be rotating and translating, then we need some way to mechanically connect
太空船到稳定的平台，但以这样的方式运动的空间
the space craft to the stable platform but in such a way that the motion of the space
工艺不会在稳定平台上引入任何扭矩或力。所以这样做的方式
craft does not introduce any torque or force on the stable platform. So the way to do that
是使用一系列万向节，所以第一个万向节是围绕这个轴旋转
is to use a series of gimbals so the first gimbal is a rotation around this axis here
然后整个组件可以围绕这个轴自由旋转，最后是所有这一切
and then that whole assembly is free to rotate around this axis and then finally all that
装配可绕该轴自由旋转。如果我们这么做，这对我们来说非常重要
assembly is free to rotate around this axis. What this allows is really important, if we
测量每个万向节中轴的角度，然后告诉我们方向
measure the angles of the shaft in each of the gimbals then that tells us the orientation
相对于稳定平台的车辆。这就是这种车辆的能力
of the vehicle with respect to the stable platform. And that's how this vehicle is able
确定它在太空中的方向。当第二个角度出现问题时
to determine it's orientation in space. The problem occurs when the angle of the second
万向节接近或减去90度，这就是称为万向节的条件
gimbal approaches plus or minus 90 degrees and that's the condition referred to as Gimbal
锁定在影片剪辑中提到。
Lock which was mentioned in the movie clip.
对于航天器导航它的工作原理是这样的，我们有这个内部元素
For space craft navigation it works something like this, we have this inner element which
被称为一个稳定的平台，它有三个正交的陀螺仪和
is referred to as a stable platform, it's got three orthogonal gyroscopes on it and
这意味着平台相对于平台保持恒定的方向
what that means is that the platform maintains a constant orientation with respect to the
宇宙。这是一个非常令人印象深刻的事情，然后太空船与另一个相连
universe. It's a very impressive thing, the space craft then is attached to the other
万向节机制的一面。因此，航天器的方向随着时间的推移而变化
side of the gimbal mechanism. So as the space craft's orientation changes over time by reading
在万向节角度，我们可以确定航天器相对于稳定的方向
the gimbal angles we can determine the orientation of the space craft with respect to the stable
平台的方向是一个常数。
platform whose orientation is a constant.
让我们考虑车辆方向以滚动表示的情况，
Let's consider the case where the orientation of the vehicle is expressed in terms of roll,
俯仰，偏航角度。我们把它写成一系列基本旋转，一个旋转
pitch, yaw angles. We write this as a sequence of elementary rotations, a rotation around
X轴由滚动角度，绕Y轴旋转的俯仰角和旋转
the X axis by the roll angle, rotation around the Y axis by the pitch angle and a rotation
通过偏航角围绕Z轴。现在让我们考虑一下俯仰角时会发生什么
around the Z axis by the yaw angle. Now let's consider what happens when the pitch angle
等于90度或2弧度的pi。我们可以写这样的表达式，现在是
equals 90 degrees or pi on 2 radians. We can write the expression like this, now the
俯仰角等于2的pi，并且有一些众所周知的身份我可以重写它
pitch angle is equal to pi on 2 and with some well known identities I can rewrite it in
这个表格。现在我们所拥有的是围绕X轴连续2次旋转，所以我可以写
this form. Now what we have is 2 consecutive rotations around the X axis so I can write
现在这是围绕X轴的单一旋转。旋转量是R+Y，它是
this now as a single rotation around the X axis. The amount of the rotation is R+Y, it's
滚动角和偏航角的总和，并且有一个最终的恒定旋转。什么
the sum of the roll angle and the yaw angle and there's a final constant rotation. What
这表明现在滚动和偏航是等价的，我们不能告诉彼此。
this indicates is that now roll and yaw are equivalent we can't tell one from another.
另一种在万向节机制方面考虑这种机械方式的方法
Another way to think about this mechanical way in terms of the Gimbal mechanism itself
是认为第一个万向节和第三个万向节的轴线现在平行于每个
is to think that the axis of the first gimbal and the third gimbal and now parallel to each
其他和对齐。这是万向节锁定现象的数学表示。
other and aligned. This is a mathematical representation of the Gimbal lock phenomenon.
并且它发生在中间万向节的角度接近2的pi时。这就是条件
And it occurs when the angle of the middle gimbal approaches pi on 2. This is the condition
他们在Apollo13剪辑中担心。
that they were concerned about in the Apollo 13 clip.
所以这意味着当您为任何特定车辆定义坐标系时
So what this means is when you define your coordinate system for any particular vehicle
如果你想描述它在滚动，俯仰和偏转角方面的方向
and if you want to describe it's orientation in terms of roll, pitch and yaw angles it's
重要的是，对于您的车辆的标称配置，俯仰角约为0。
important that the pitch angle is around 0 for the nominal configuration of your vehicle.
因此，如果它是飞机，那么当它处于默认水平配置时，俯仰角将为0
So if it's an aircraft then the pitch angle would be 0 when it is in default horizontal configuration
或者好像它是火箭，你会想要确保0桨距角相对应
or as if it was a rocket you would want to make sure that the 0 pitch angle corresponded
直接上升的条件。你需要确保与情况有关
to the condition of going straight up. You need to ensure that the situation with the
在正常操作条件下，不会发生俯仰角等于正负2。
pitch angle equals plus or minus 2 does not occur during normal operating conditions.